# ANDREW W. ROSS, MSc.

## **GIS Analyst**

San Diego, CA · andrew@44digits.com · 858-477-8807 Blog: www.44digits.com · LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/andrewross44

#### **SUMMARY**

Highly motivated GIS Analyst with over 9 years of experience developing and maintaining GIS maps, analyses, and geospatial data pipelines. Demonstrated experience utilizing ArcGIS and Python for creating sophisticated mapping and visualization tools to help decision-makers visualize real-world events. Passionate about performing specialized mapping and analysis in a regional planning environment.

## **SKILLS**

GIS applications: Expert in ESRI ArcGIS Pro and QGIS

- including Spatial Analyst, 3D Analyst, and Network Analyst extensions

Advanced skills in relational database management systems

- including Oracle Spatial, Postgres/PostGIS

Proficient in compiling and integrating data from multiple GIS sources

Programming & scripting: Python programming with ArcPy, GeoPandas, Numpy, Scipy

<u>SQL</u>: spatial queries, stored procedures, functions

Machine learning with PyTorch Development of Spatial ETL pipelines

Test-Driven Python development with Pytest

Spatial API development with FastAPI

Cloud platforms: AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner Certification

Azure Fundamentals Certification

Docker containerization setup and management

Technical proficiencies: Excellent proficiency with Microsoft Office

VS Code, GIT version control, Linux and shell scripting

## **EXPERIENCE**

**Congruex**GIS Engineer

San Diego, CA June 2020 - Current

- Developed and deployed a cloud-based API infrastructure using <u>Python FastAPI on Azure</u> to deliver 19 geospatial analysis, reporting, and data management services, enhancing functionality of mapping system for various departments at Congruex
- Engineered data analyses in Python with Jupyter Notebooks, GeoPandas, Shapely and other spatial libraries increasing access to corporate spatial data warehouse for project managers
- Trained GIS staff to support management of corporate mapping platform ensuring reliability and stability of spatial database, map servers, GIT, Linux and concomitant systems
- Provided end-user support and training to technical and non-GIS users of corporate web-mapping platform
- Dramatically improved speed and efficiency of support staff tasks by making routine geoprocessing workflows faster and more efficient; deploying tools and automations for data <u>verification and</u> management utilizing Jupyter Notebooks in Python for Geoserver and Postgres
- Created automated data cleaning and verification <u>spatial ETL pipeline</u> to consolidate geospatial data from partner organizations processing over 13 million features per day using containerized infrastructure on Azure

**Freelance** San Diego, CA Data Analyst January 2019 - May 2020

- Developed and deployed targeted surveys providing insights into customer engagement and product utilization
- Improved results by closely collaborating with clients to thoroughly understand their needs and requirements
- Increased scale and analysis turnaround by automating end-to-end process to verify, clean, consolidate and analyze data in Python and ArcPy
- Improved depth of analysis by incorporating related spatial data and creating reporting pipeline in ArcGIS Pro

**BC Transit** GIS Analyst

Victoria, Canada January 2013 - October 2018

- Worked closely with planning and administrative staff to develop GIS maps and suitability analyses consolidating relevant up-to-date spatial information to directly support regional planning, asset management, and capital improvement projects
- Deployed spatial ETL pipeline, built with Python and Jupyter Notebooks, processing 150,000+ transactions per day from a fleet of 700+ vehicles providing detailed insights into transport ridership patterns
- Developed performance metrics system to monitor security and quality of regional reporting systems improving alerting and notification of farebox security incidents and technical problems
- Created continuous monitoring system with multiple departments ensuring uninterrupted stream of ridership data providing up to date statistical reports and analysis
- Performed GIS models and spatial analyses on ridership data for administrative and planning departments, preparing reports and summaries in ArcGIS, directly supporting decision making for the management and planning of the transit network
- Ongoing GIS data maintenance, manipulation, analysis, extraction, and generation and managing organizational geospatial data warehouse
- Received the 2015 corporate Recognizing Excellence and Values award for helping to create a cross-departmental team that significantly improved transit vehicle farebox data collection

## **EDUCATION**

**Udacity Nanodegree** 

Bertelsmann Scholarship, AI Programming with Python

Queen's University Kingston, Canada

Master of Science, Computer Science

**University of Ottawa** Ottawa, Canada

Graduate Diploma, International Development

**Queen's University** Kingston, Canada

Bachelor of Science, Psychology & Computer Science